okay okay we're ready i will start the presentation
tell me you can see me
yes so i can see okay here we are
okay uh as i said we are talking i think that you really know if we talk about the spice
what we are talking about isn't it uh i'm sorry to interrupt you uh can we record this video
yeah yeah can you record it and also if you do it and then you can send it to me which should be a
good thing because i had to but i'm not actually i can do this with for some problems so if you
record it and send it to me uh it will be a very good thing sorry to interrupt ciao gabriele thanks
for the lesson i just connected for the sole purpose of recording so i am recording the
the lesson and i will okay okay so i won't be active in the lesson just here for record okay
thanks yeah good thing because i have problems with my microphone so i am using uh i think to
to present and i think to uh talk because i wish to do this it would be a very good thing thank you
okay thanks okay so we start uh we are talking about uh a spice and
uh how you can uh read on the on the here the proposal of the spice is to improve and value the
performance of the development process and ecosystem of industry industries uh it is a specific variant of
international standard diesel and actually it allows the best way to have a good process to uh fulfill our
project to do our things and uh i think that you already know uh something about the bicycle
that is a cycle that is used in a spice to uh develop a good software i think that you should
already know the the thesis about uh develop and testing today we'll talk about the requirement part
that is uh in the up and the left part of the cycle uh you can see here that we have uh more parts of
this uh requirement uh um requirement part and uh here we can you can read that we have
the requirement elicitation uh the system requirement analysis and software requirement because if we're
talking about uh the development of software we have a level for uh system requirement uh analysis that
will tell you uh what do we what do our system have to do what can the kind of things have we have to
develop and how the the part of software requirement analysis that will tell us which software with
which implementation will do the things that uh we need to uh fulfill our system requirements
uh we start with some definition and some properties that uh our requirements uh need
need to be a good thing actually just to give you a better introduction uh the rest of our work will be
some documents uh that will be stored in our cases in some server and in these documents it will be all
the description of our work but we have to find a proper way to do this thing a first definition that
we can have is the difference between the functional requirement that is uh what the system shall do
and not the functional requirement that is uh what the system shall be the difference is that in the
second one is a moral description of the system uh while a functional requirement is a description of
our implementation and all the things that we do have to work so a definition for example of an
inputs outputs and the procedure of our software
a good writing requirement should have some characteristics the first one is that should be
clear and ambiguous so there should be only one way to interpret the requirement let's see some
examples if we frame right and the system shall not accept the password longer than 15 characters
actually we don't have a good description because we don't know actually if uh something different
from this is possible if uh a password of 16 cards arrives to us what the system shall do and we actually
don't know so it's important to to write something like if the user is the password longer than 15 characters
then the system shall display an error message and shall ask the user to correct it so we describe the all the
things that system do does and we don't have some misinterpretation of of our functionalities
every requirement that we write should be stable the requirement can be refined by means of inspection
analysis demonstration of tests for example if you write a system must refresh the data very quickly we don't have
uh a way to test this thing because uh uh this is not the description that can be uh it can have an
representation for everyone the same so a good requirement should be the system has refresh the data each
0 5 milliseconds we can actually test these things because for example if the data refresh more than this time
we can tell that the task the test the test is failed
uh the requirements should be feasible the requirements should be double with existing constraints
um for example the replacement control system shall be styled with this no disruption of the production
but the good requirement should be the replacement control c but uh control system shall be started
causing no more than two days of production destruction just because usually on the
software on the software on the hardware we have some uh constraints and we should respect it for
example we cannot demand a system that can avoid the physical constraints or it should be do things
faster than our technology allow us to do our things
there are a lot of other properties that will speed up on these things it should be consistent
uh because we should uh we probably have a full document with a lot of things and a requirement of
functionality should not interfere with other requirements so uh the book should be a consistent uh
consistency about all the things we have it should be atomic because uh for example uh since we have
uh it's it depends on the testable property because uh uh at each requirement we should
uh assign a test and if you wait if you write the things like um in case of our temperature over current
over over state over both the system shall board the change but actually um here we have a true
requirement because we should have three tests assigned to this property because for example uh we respect
the part of our temperature probably our current is not implemented and the over voltage doesn't work
and if we don't have a uh right like in the like above uh we should not plan um test for everything that we have
and should not um find which things works which not with which parts have errors and when we have to change
uh our work and last things it should be traceable um since i i said you before that uh we have more level requirements
system parts or per part and also the test we should have a traceability between all the parts of our documents
so if you have a software required script and implementation we should know uh where this implementation comes from
for which functionality we have to do these things and we will see how these things is done
in some software that i will show you later
we switch to the other slides
this one
i said you before that there are some software that we use to implement the requirements uh in the slide
before the word there are some slides about uh about a software named doors but i will show you
something more about another software this is called polaro because i gave the license here
and the slides show you some things about the software but later in the end of the lesson we have a
quick introduction to this software how to use it and uh other section and all the things are done
so we start with the slides from some bit introduction and then we will see on the software uh some example
actually um uh the requirement documents appears like like this and it's a document with a lot of
objects you can see that we have uh usually uh this is a screen about polarion and here we have a
description description description of our things and uh in the right part in the left part we have a
code and unique code that is associated with a single requirement um actually if we do some change
change and uh we've or we delete this requirement this code will still be assigned to this one because we
have to have just a bit in the time about our documents here in the left we have an icon an icon that
actually uh see us what kind of requirement is this because we have an icon for software we will have
uh an icon icon for system an icon for uh for text and more in the right part we have uh some properties
we can usually cast on these things that because because uh our item our requirement is not just a
description but is anything with a lot of properties that say us a lot of things about how to develop
so for example um these properties can be the severity let's say at last um if the this requirement
is a must have a should evidence to have or something that is deprecated they will not have to implement
it is very useful for developers because it's good to set some priority because in the when we drop we
probably start with must have things and then when everything is finishing test and we can
we can go to should dev and later to the other the others
there is here a status that tells us uh the status of the requirement not the status of the
implementation because when we write probably we start usually we start from a drop status
uh when we write the things when you have the finished to write we uh switch back to uh i
review the average status and then in a probably verified rejected uh and also this uh machine can
change you know how many people work on the things online level of people that can review approve and test
things but the important part is when we are here we can make some modification later we cannot if we
want to modify our require when you have to come back this is start to the status so i will we will
see you later in polaro that we if if we are not in draft the document the the requirement is blocked
um here uh we can see also other properties like dd that we can see also in the document
but also uh the traceability part because here i've written uh which should the requirements are
connected to this one um as parent is referred to uh uh to the leader of the chapter for example and
it's related to his pro here is a relation with another item in another document
so uh with these links we can fulfill accessibility between them with between documents but we will
see an example later uh here we showed for example that here it was a requirement about uh can message
that says that that information used in the system is uh carried by this message and in that link we can
connect with the description of the message with other properties that we can find in the dbc
uh also this is another view that we will uh you will see uh later in the software that
it is a representation with all the levels uh just to have a better interpretation of how many links that
could we have and here uh have some on uh some of charts that we can have because uh as you said
before we are using a proper software to do these things uh actually we could also use some uh an excel
not word because we have a lot of properties but an excel should be good and also we will see that we can
uh every reporting from polarion to excel but the good things to have a software that is done just
for this is because it can give us some uh for some reports that can be used to have a global view of
our project for example here we have a coverage report that tell us that a part of our requirement got
the coverage and that part doesn't so later we can print a report discovering which part which
requirement doesn't have a coverage and uh complete our our documents but also uh some graphic about
the develop to treat to have trees about uh how things are done what things are done what which not
and so we can have a better view of our project
here another report uh i i took up before about coverage report uh here we can see that for
example a system requirement have a software requirement have a software requirement assigned
but the order doesn't so we can know uh that we are still to write some software requirement and
where and about which functionalities
this is another view of the same report but in a table way
and before we uh continue with this part i will tell you if you have some questions
if everything is clear of if you have some questions about these things
okay
um just a little things um why these things is important because uh uh if we work in uh automotive
uh environment but also in other uh environment and it is uh secretica for example for uh um
for uh for train for uh for planes we should have um a develop that follow a lot of rules because we cannot
um release a software that have problems if we sell a car with the software that have bugs we should
uh uh have we should have some problem that could cause people to die cars to stop working
and so in different uh difference from us other kindle software for example um from uh um
um cell phone software from some app that could be work could be crash and uh sometimes a new version
of software released the software car should not be updated should be should uh be uh should uh should
work from the day one and should not the problem because uh uh the risk that of these things that is
sometimes very high so uh that's for this that we have to uh have developed that starts from requirement
then the develop the testing and all the parts that can show us that everything is done and everything is done correctly
here we have um a test report that also is made by polarion
because every um um after that we have written everything that our software needs after develop
we should start with the testing part so we should write the test associated to our implementation
and then run some test run that tell us uh for example here we have test run which three tests
we can execute this and then we can report that uh which some tests are passed some tests are waiting
uh and we have other two status so failed and blocked that's because probably uh some tests depends on the
result on other one probably have to start the car uh to do 10 meters and then to do to try to to stop the
car if the second part is not fulfilled you cannot test the third part so uh we can have the block test
because the test has been not be done because the previous one failed so we we can we could not try
this thing and so when we try our things we have these three status which tell us which things gone good
and which one bad how we write our test here we should usually have a step instead i start up here for
example and the expected result and uh here we can select if test is passive either blocking and i write
if it failed the block actually the we can write the actual result for which happen and not for the
developer to find the bugs errors and the correction that has to be done
also the test should be have just a bit with software so we spare software we have just a bit with
uh with the with the test and the test uh should be connected with the bug founded if the test is not
be done and here in plan we also can store the bug uh the change and everything that uh should
give us a good responsibility of all of all our work in the time
okay before to proceed with this part we will have a little a better view of this thing on the software
any question
okay excuse me i have a question yeah that part that you were explaining about the hierarchy of the
requirement can you explain a little bit more about it
i can hear you very well if you can repeat
uh you were explaining a little bit about the hierarchy of the requirements
i don't know it was too much uh before so
okay hello we will give you some example right this paper so you understand
how we better how these things works okay thank you
let's find some project we can play with
okay this is a browser um a software that can can make us to navigate by browser so actually i'm
working in chrome and i can connect to this software uh inserting the the ep of the server that should be an
internal ep actually is set here enables uh i'm working uh already on the server so we just i just have localhost
but otherwise you should input to the ep and the program service then when you log in with
uh your user and password you arrive here here we have the name of project and you can navigate with older project
this is the home in home we find the description on uh on uh every part of our project
that you can find here in this part let's see something hello here we start with
let's be slow
with the requirements section here we have um description like input and output because uh we
start with the project scope where it is bright and everything about the project uh in um in a not
specific way so we have also the evolution plan uh responsibilities a lot of information about
our project and uh starting from this document we have enough to put about a system required
specification document
here the second level
let's see for example
we'll we'll just make a little change to
have you so you can see the things better
uh
here we are in this document it is about document about the system required specification we have
all these items of you uh you can see the the id here a title and here a description
um it is actually a test project it's not a really project that we use but it's just used for
uh academy for for testing for uh allow people to try some functionalities of the software
but actually here we can see uh some system requirement for example that should be an easy
to operate with excessive training things like this
and um here on the right we have some properties that are displayed on the document and here in the
the right panel we can modify these properties and we have the severity the status since for example the
status is reviewed if you try to write something it's actually not in change but if we
uh perform an action rework and we save the document
with a little weight the status of our item change and now we are able to write something
in the requirement and make some modification when we are done we save
a bit slow today it's a bit slow today and we perform an actual review so we block this description
of the data um in this part usually you have some uh description of the system so description of
functionalities and not a proper description of the implementation that you have in the next part here
in the design part
we have input to the previous document and as output to the software software requirements
specification document with a description of the implementation here we can find some uml
we can find some input description we can find a lot of things here here are some
examples but it depends a lot of uh which project we are we are describing uh you can find some uh text
description but also some pseudo code usually some uh part of code so a lot of things uh some figures
and if we navigate it we can find that for example software requirement item is connected to a system required
document uh system requirement item but also it it is verified by some from some tests that we can find in the next session
if we go back
the same part we also have here the software test case specification if we open this document we'll find
all the tests that are associated to our software items with some steps some step description and some expected
record record results when someone want to test these things it should create a text section
test session add this item to access it to the test section session and uh try it and report the result
here we have a different uh way to read it because uh uh the test part is always made by
a table with the steps and other things we can actually uh customize this part but we always save the table for the
three or four part of our more part of our test
and just to give you some more information
we go back to the software requirement specification part and we give a better look to the single item
here uh i said before that here we have some properties that are already shown the document
here we are some probably that you can we can change the properties but if you open the item
we have a full look about the single item with all the properties um uh that it have priority
initial estimate i spent a lot of things and also some custom properties that we that we can add to
the item uh but to add some custom properties we should navigate in the
um in the administration part i will not show you uh actually it's today because uh it is a things that
uh is by the only usually but uh by people that administrate the project and the usual the work that
uh user uh does is to fulfill the information not to customize but if someone uh uh needs this part
we can uh make another quick lesson introduction to customize project uh but let's see some of the
most important things here on uh upright we have the history
that uh show us actually this is not uh realistic because we no action on these things but uh usually
here we have all the version of the item because uh uh we could change the uh our description for
example 10 times and here we could find probably if we just to see another one
okay here we have uh some two uh version of this item that tell us that this has been modified two
years ago or three years ago so here we can see the action of the modification and with these things we can
see the history of an item or the history of the document because usually uh we could uh we probably
we could want to know how these things things change in the times and and we want to retrospective
some implementation to know for example uh in that uh one years before what was the description of
these things because actually description exchange and implementation with it
so to have a repository actually it uh polarion implements a repository that can allow us to see
the history of item documents and also the history of the older project
for all the project we have a section section here above that is baseline section actually we have no
baseline saved but uh the difference between history and baseline is that here we can create a baseline
for today for example today we have release we can delete a baseline tool for the release and we have
we can navigate all the project in that day for the for the status in the day that we create the baseline so
um it's not about the single item but this is old items so we can navigate we can change documents and
see all the things that was done in uh probably for one hour one year before or the day of a specific release
here instead we have in the first part here we have a lot of section for the parts of our develop
uh i just to do the you the required the same part but uh we have also the risk part the development part
of trace develop and the maintenance that we will not see because actually is um all the same scheme
and uh it's not so important to see all of them
actually we have some other documents for the sky in this part that is still connected to the previous one
but let's go to see other things about the software
um here we have some section with documents and item but if if we want to explore this um
not the section but for example all the system requirements that can be stored in more documents
here we have a section with all work item that we can open and we can see all the objects that are
storing documents so we have not a document view but the table view of all things that we have we can
filter here for type for example or we can create here filters about i don't know some properties for
example all the item that is should have and we can load the table about all the item for example that
has been created from someone or that have a association with some things
and it is good because also we can export these things with an excel file
we can select which properties we want to export usually there is always the id the title
and also the description but you can see that the first three are blocked for example the quart
the fourth one no id is always blocked because we can't not change it because it's assigned by the
software but for example we can we can uh want to unblock the description because we want to export
this excel to someone that don't have this of the access to polarion but we want that you can add some
more text description to some to some item and then when when we do these things i will just show you
when we export this and we modify the excel we actually can re-import the excel and import all the
modification this is why polarity is not also software when where you want to work but it's uh first a
storageable document and not all people that work here should be have the access to all the information
all the items all the things but probably we just want to export a file to someone that probably could
be also in some other society some other part of the world we share this thing with him here we see
that since we have the the title block and he cannot change anything but it can change the description part
add some things save this file and send it back to us and we can run the import part and we can
update our storage of our documents and our items
instead here we have a document section with all the documents for divided for
for part design development etc and we can see all the documents but also the report associated to
documents i showed you some of this report before in the slides and here where you can find it
also we have a dashboard farm that we can customize where there is all the graphs that we can need to
understand the status of our project so how many issues we have how many of them in process how many
change requests uh and all other things that we need but we can create more charts about things that we want
to have a quick view to administrate properly the our our project
okay some questions
okay so we'll take a quick break of 10 minutes and we will do the other slides that
uh we have to explain to finish the lesson so see you back in 10 minutes
see you
so
you
Thank you.